Finding Aid for Lew Allen Chase papers, 1820-1955
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lew Allen Chase papers 1820-1955 1894-1927
Chase, Lew Allen, 1879-1957.
1 linear foot and 1 oversize folder
85996 Aa 2; UAm
Professor of history at Northern Michigan University in Marquette, Michigan; correspondence, family materials, scrapbooks, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of George F. Chase (donor no. 3379 ) and Alberta Chase (donor no. 3376 ) and came to the library in 1958-1959. The scrapbook dated 1905-1955 was the gift of Shirley Wheeler Smith (donor no. 1718 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Lew Allen Chase was born in Elsie, Michigan, Nov. 13, 1879. He graduated from the Michigan School for the Blind and from Lansing High School in 1901.
Chase married the former Charlotte Pearce in 1903 and later enrolled in the University of Michigan. A victim of hereditary blindness, he was able to carry on his college studies by having his wife and other students read his texts and lecture notes to him. He received his A.B. degree in 1910 and his M.A. degree in 1911.
Chase was an instructor in history at the Hancock and Houghton High Schools from 1911 to 1919, when he joined the faculty of Northern Michigan College. He was head of the college's Department of History until 1940 when it was merged with the Department of Social Sciences. Chase became head of that department also and retained this position until he retired from the college in 1944.
Chase was a member and past president of the Michigan Academy of Sciences, Arts and Letter, the Michigan Historical Commission and the Michigan Historical Society. He was active in the Marquette County Historical Society and served as its corresponding secretary for many years. He also was a member of the American Political Science Association, the American Historical Association,. and the Missouri Historical Society. His affiliations also included membership on the Library of Congress Advisory Committee on Books for the Blind.
He was the author of two books, The Government of Michigan and Rural Michigan and wrote articles for Mining Journal and other publications. He died May 21, 1957.
The Chase collection consists of correspondence, family materials, scrapbooks, and photographs. The correspondence dates from 1894 to 1955. One folder of letters is between Chase and James Cochran in which they discuss southern and northern attitudes toward Blacks. The family materials include letters of his mother Delia to Clara and Mary Noyes, and thirteen letters of the Chase-Beach family. There are also genealogical papers and a manuscript of "Personal Recollections of the Civil War" by Delia Chase. The scrapbook series includes letters, clippings, programs and photographs. One volume concerns Wilbert B. Hinsdale, Northern Michigan University, the Michigan School for the Blind in Lansing, and the Chase family. Correspondents include: James B. Angell, Harriet Bates, Alberta Chase, Cornelia Chase, George W. Chase, Edna Ferber, Archibald MacLeish, Thomas Mann, Ambrose M. Shotwell, Shirley W. Smith, Isabel Van Tyne, and Alexander Woolcott.
Subjects:
Bates family.; Chase, Cornelia, 1815-1905.; Chase, Lew Allen, 1879-1957.; Elsie (Mich.); Hinsdale, W. B. (Wilbert B.), 1851-1944.; Michigan Historical Commission.; Michigan School for the Blind.; Northern Michigan College of Education.; Pearce family.; Tabor family.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Beach family.; Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Chase, Lew Allen, 1879-1957.; Chase family.
Contributors:
Chase, Alberta.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Bates, Harriet.; Chase, Delia A.; Chase, George Willey, b. 1840.; Ferber, Edna, 1887-1968.; Jandy, Edward Clarence, 1899-; Lincoln, Mary Todd, 1818-1882.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955.; Shotwell, Ambrose Milton, 1853-; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Van Tyne, Isabel.; Woollcott, Alexander, 1887-1943.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - By date
    - 1894 (Box 1)
    - 1895 (Box 1)
    - 1896 (Box 1)
    - 1897 (Box 1)
    - 1898 (Box 1)
    - 1899 (Box 1)
    - 1900 (Box 1)
    - 1901 (Box 1)
    - 1905-1925 (Box 1)
    - 1926-1955 (Box 1)
  - With James A. Cochran, 1927 (Box 1)
- Family materials
  - Chase-Beach family correspondence, 1820-1908 (Box 1)
  - Chase family history (Box 1)
  - Materials used in preparation of Chase family history (Box 1)
  - D.A. Chase (personal recollections of the Civil War), 1903 (Box 1)
  - Delia Chase (mother of Lew Allen Chase)
    - Letters to Clara and Mary Noyes, 1868-1880 (Box 1)
    - Reminiscences of Delia Chase's girlhood during the Civil War, typescript copy (Box 1)
- Photographs, Scrapbooks, etc.
  - Miscellaneous 1908-1948 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folder UAm)
  - Scrapbook containing letters, newspaper clippings, programs, photographs relating to the Chase, Pearce and Beach families of Elsie, Michigan; also concerns Wilbert B. Hinsdale, Northern Michigan University, and the Michigan School for the Blind, 1905-1955 (Box 1)
    (This volume also contains single letters from Edna Ferber, Archibald MacLeish, and Thomas Mann)
  - Scrapbook containing clippings of poetry, human interest stories, etc., ca. 1880-ca. 1910 (Box 1)